<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-06-11T23:05:31+00:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Belkirk College of Engineering</title><subtitle>Belkirk Demo Site for Forestry.io</subtitle><entry><title type="html">What is DnDMake?</title><link href="/2017-09-25-introduction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is DnDMake?" /><published>2017-09-25T09:09:13+00:00</published><updated>2017-09-25T09:09:13+00:00</updated><id>/introduction</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2017-09-25-introduction/">&lt;p&gt;Dungeons and Dragons has experienced a renaissance in recent years. Appearances in popular media and the rise of the video game generation have all but removed the heavy stigma of nerdiness, and led to an influx of new players both young and old. The most recent 5th edition (5E) is  the most accessible of all time, and the digital era is dramatically lowering the barriers to access content and resources about the game. However, despite all the new interest DnD remains one of the most hardcore experiences you can have in gaming,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tabletop wargames that inspired DND focused heavily on simulating reality and replicating real physical scenarios. They were laden with pages and pages of technical rules and stat sheets, with almost nothing overlooked in the name of realism. They appealed specifically to a core audience of history or simulation enthusiasts who were interested in exploring the specifics of a given scenario, and implementing intricate strategies within a clearly defined universe. DND carries much of this complexity with it, resulting in a rule box hundreds of pages long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;## So What’s the Problem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While DnD has a strong core following, the majority of new audience members are intimidated by a a ruleset magnitudes larger than anything they have experienced before. Players are expected to have read and absorbed ideas like attack rolls, skill checks, resistances, HP and damage, movement rules, reactions, the action economy, the separation of player and character and much more. While there is an aspect of ‘learning on the go’ where mechanics are drip-fed, the sheer bulk of rulesets means players are almost guaranteed to spend their first one or two sessions floundering, and likely still making mistakes and errors months into their first campaign. For some, the cognitive load of multiple layers of rulesets will simply never go away;  they will never ‘get’ DnD and walk away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the game of DND has a strong narrative tradition set in Tolkeineque medieval fantasy, meaning it is assumed players are familiar with classic narrative concepts like elves, dwarves, kingdoms, quests, wizards, gods, demons, dungeons and monsters. While its possible to jump straight in without any experience in these genre tropes, having to learn and interact with these new concepts introduced yet another barrier in the way of ‘getting’ the game in any decent time frame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the above represents a massive hurdle in the way of the players experiencing magical mix of teamwork, problem solving and narrative construction that makes roleplaying games so unique and compelling. For those with the perseverance to get through the first few sessions, a limitless world of play awaits them. But for the majority, spending twenty to forty hours learning rules, systems and the ins and outs of roleplaying just to ‘play the game’ is simply a bridge too far. The result is the huge swathe of new and excited players leaving DND behind with the famous line of ‘I tried it, but it’s just not for me’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;## What do we do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal of this project is to break DnD down into its smallest constituent parts, while retaining the core features that make it what it is. By doing this we hope to craft a roleplaying experience that retains the famous ‘feel’ of DND, while reducing the technical complexity and cognitive burden of play that presents a barrier of entry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For new players it should mean being able to pick up the game and start playing at a relatively high level within a single session, rapidly accelerating them towards the magical ‘aha’ moment that makes them roleplayers for life. For DND veterans it will be a faster, more freeform roleplaying experience that may highlight the cumbersome nature of classic rules they never thought to question. And for the design enthusiasts out there it’s a worthwhile opportunity to dissect a system that’s matured over it’s half century of development, but still has a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recommending changes we will be following a core set of design goals:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Lower the barrier of entry for new DND players&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Reduce cognitive load on both players and DM to play&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Encourage teamwork, roleplay and creativity in problem solving&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Discourage activities that are uninteractive, procedural or * purely calculative&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Speed up the game to reduce inactive player time (specifically combat)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Remove or simplify any features that do one or more of the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Require static tracking of numbers&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Require lists and/or lookup tables to function&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Have a dedicated and self-enclosed rule system&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;## Analysis Structure&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For this analysis we will be compartmentalising the many core systems, rulesets and mechanics in DND where it makes sense, then breaking them down into the simplest form that can still be considered true to the game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the process we will be dissecting what the mechanic does for the game, its history and whether its important to keep some or any of its features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally we will propose one or more new ruleset to replace the old, with variants depending on how far users wish to simplify their game&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Articles are structured as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Summary of existing ruleset / mechanic&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Analysis of what the rule does and why its valuable to DND&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Critique of the rule in its current form&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Statement of intent of any changes&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Suggested rule change&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The result should be a concise series of design analysis articles on each of DND’s systems, and a drastically stripped back ruleset which can be used to run a game of DND.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With no further ado, let’s break down DnD.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Dungeons and Dragons has experienced a renaissance in recent years. Appearances in popular media and the rise of the video game generation have all but removed the heavy stigma of nerdiness, and led to an influx of new players both young and old. The most recent 5th edition (5E) is the most accessible of all time, and the digital era is dramatically lowering the barriers to access content and resources about the game. However, despite all the new interest DnD remains one of the most hardcore experiences you can have in gaming,</summary></entry></feed>